<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Alexandra Nikoltchovska</title><link>https://nikoltchovska.de/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Alexandra Nikoltchovska</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 10:31:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nikoltchovska.de/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>IBM Model 1 Machine Translation in Python</title><link>https://nikoltchovska.de/posts/ibm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 10:31:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://nikoltchovska.de/posts/ibm/</guid><description>&lt;p>The IBM model 1 is the original gangster of statistical machine translation.
It can learn a dictionary between two languages from a number of translated sentences
without any real understanding of language and with a complete disregard for word order.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Even though, we will see that is is able to get meaningful results even from small-ish
training sets. While the usual way of explaining its working involves alignments, I find
it much more intuitive to think about it as a variant of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_iteration">Von Mises Iteration&lt;/a>.
In both cases we iteratively move some kind of mass to the most probable solution. Constant
normalization of the solution reinforces the most probable solution while suppressing less
probable ones.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Speeding up Python with Java</title><link>https://nikoltchovska.de/posts/jpype/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 11:43:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://nikoltchovska.de/posts/jpype/</guid><description>Remember kids, 8 billion devices run Java.</description></item><item><title>How to debug NaN Values in PyTorch Models during Training</title><link>https://nikoltchovska.de/posts/torch_nans/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 10:31:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://nikoltchovska.de/posts/torch_nans/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s really slow.</description></item><item><title>The overengineered Solution to my Pigeon Problem</title><link>https://nikoltchovska.de/posts/pigeons/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 12:05:06 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://nikoltchovska.de/posts/pigeons/</guid><description>&lt;p>TL;DR: I built a wifi-equipped water gun to shoot
the pigeons on my balcony, controlled over the internet by a
python script running openCV reading the camera image of my
old iPhone.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The pigeons in my backyard find particular pleasures in voiding their excrements onto my balcony. Dissatisfied with this situation, I went online to find a solution. I created a handy table to give you an overview of the vast number of &lt;del>effective&lt;/del> &lt;em>established&lt;/em> ways to get rid if pigeons:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>